John Wieners Papers
John Wieners Papers
1955-1970
Wieners, John, 1934-2002.
0.75 linear ft.
Papers of the American poet. Incoming and out going correspondence (1956-1964); manuscripts and galley proofs for Ace of Pentacles; typescript poems and short stories; a diary dated 1955-1956; a notebook containing holograph poems; and newspaper clippings and articles about avant-garde writers. Correspondents include James Broughton, James F. Carr, Cid Corman, Gregory Corso, Robert Creeley, Robert Duncan, Allen Ginsberg, Jack Kerouac, Philip Lamantia, Michael McClure, Archibald MacLeish, W.S. Merwin, Marianne Moore, Philip Whalen, and Jonathan Williams.
148756
Biographical History
Poet John Wieners was born in Boston on January 6, 1934. After graduating from Boston College in 1954, Wieners attended Black Mountain College from 1955-1956, studying under Charles Olson and Robert Duncan. He became associated with the Poet's Theatre in Cambridge, and his two one-act plays were produced by the New York Poet's Theatre and Judson Poets Theatre in New York. In 1957 he founded the poetry magazine, Measure, and in 1962 received the Poet's Foundation Award. Among his published books are The Hotel Wentley Poems (1958), Ace of Pentacles (1964), Pressed Wafer (1967), Asylum Poems (For my Father) (1969), Youth (1970), Nerves (1970), Selected Poems (1972), and Behind the State Capitol, Or Cincinnati Pike (1975).
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The John Wieners Papers consists of a Subject file, Correspondence, Writings, and Published material.
The Subject file contains biographical information. The Correspondence includes letters from various poets, many of whom contributed to Measure, a poetry journal which Wieners edited. All correspondence is incoming unless otherwise noted. The Writings consist of the manuscript, galley proofs, and other materials relating to Wieners' book Ace of Pentacles; a journal produced between 1955 and 1956; a notebook; typescript poems; and two untitled pieces: a short story, and a book manuscript. The Printed material includes book reviews and publicity items for Ace of Pentacles, photocopies of Measure issues, and an assortment of articles and newspaper clippings about avant-garde writers.
Arrangement of the Collection
Material is arranged alphabetically. Within the correspondence folders, each folder is arranged chronologically.
Subject and Genre Headings
Radicalism; Literature -- American Poetry; Literature -- American Fiction; Broughton, James Richard, 1913-1999.; Carr, James F.; Corman, Cid.; Corso, Gregory.; Creeley, Robert, 1926-2005.; Duncan, Robert Edward, 1919-1988.; Ginsberg, Allen, 1926-1997.; Kerouac, Jack, 1922-1969.; Lamantia, Philip, 1927-2005.; McClure, Michael.; MacLeish, Archibald, 1892-1982.; Merwin, W. S. (William Stanley), 1927-; Moore, Marianne, 1887-1972.; Whalen, Philip.; Wieners, John, 1934-2002.; Williams, Jonathan, 1929-2008.; American literature -- 20th century.; American poetry -- 20th century.; Poets, American.; Literature, Experimental.; Bohemianism -- United States.; Correspondence.; Diaries.; Galley proofs.; Manuscripts for publication.; Poets.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Subject file
  - Biographical material (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Broughton, James, 1957; undated (Box 1)
  - Carr, James F., 1964 (Box 1)
  - Corman, Cid, 1957 (Box 1)
  - Corso, Gregory, 1957-1958 (Box 1)
  - Creeley, Robert, 1957-1959 (Box 1)
  - Duncan, Robert, 1956-1957; includes typescripts (originals and reproducions) of poems by Duncan (Box 1)
  - Ginsberg, Allen, 1956-1959 (Box 1)
  - Kerouac, Jack, [1956] (Box 1)
  - Lamantia, Philip, 1959; includes typescripts of poems by Lamantia (Box 1)
  - MacLeish, Archibald, undated (Box 1)
  - McClure, Michael, undated (Box 1)
  - Merwin, W. S., 1957 (Box 1)
  - Moore, Marianne, 1957 (Box 1)
  - Perkins, Michael, 1967-1970; outgoing (Box 1)
    Purchased, 2013.
  - Posner, David, undated; photocopies only (Box 1)
  - Whalen, Philip, 1957 (Box 1)
  - Williams, Jonathan, 1957-1958 (Box 1)
- Writings
  - Books
    - Ace of Pentacles, Manuscript; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Ace of Pentacles, Cover design (rejected) (Box 1)
    - Ace of Pentacles, Table of contents (Box 1)
    - Ace of Pentacles, Dummy (Box 1)
    - Ace of Pentacles, Galley proofs with holograph notes and corrections; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Journal
    - 1955-1956 (Box 1)
  - Manuscript
    - Untitled (appears to be for a book) (Box 1)
  - Notebook
    - Notes, addresses, holograph poems (Box 2)
  - Poems
    - "The Acts of Youth" (Box 2)
    - "An Anniversary of Death" (Box 2)
    - "Ballade" (Box 2)
    - "Le Chariot" (Box 2)
    - "Exchange of the Lady's Handmaids" (Box 2)
    - "If Love Be Dark" (Box 2)
    - "The Ladies" (Box 2)
    - "The Mermaid's Song" (Box 2)
    - "On January 20th the Snows Began to Melt" (Box 2)
    - "Poem" (Box 2)
    - "A Poem for the Dead I Know" (Box 2)
    - "A Poem for Trapped Things" (Box 2)
    - "Second Flight Across Country" (Box 2)
    - "Spring 1956" (Box 2)
    - "The Swan" (Box 2)
    - "Two First Poems" (Box 2)
    - "Two Years Later" (Box 2)
    - "Where Fled" (Box 2)
    - "You Can't Kill These Machines" (Box 2)
  - Short Story
    - Untitled (Box 2)
- Printed material
  - Books
    - Ace of Pentacles, Autographed tip-in pages (Box 2)
    - Ace of Pentacles, Book reviews (Box 2)
    - Ace of Pentacles, Publicity (miscellaneous) (Box 2)
    - Ace of Pentacles, Publisher's advertisements (Box 2)
  - Newspaper clippings
    - Avant-garde writers, 4 folders
      - New York Review of Books, Oct. 31, 1963 (Box 2)
      - New York Sunday Herald Tribune Magazine, May 17, 1964 (Box 2)
      - Times Literary Supplement, Aug. 6, 1964 (Box 2)
      - "The Mimeograph Revolution" from the Times Literary Supplement, Aug. 6, 1964 (Box 2)
  - Periodicals
    - Measure (edited by John Wieners)
      - no. 1, (photocopy), Summer 1957 (Box 2)
      - no. 2, (photocopy), Winter 1958 (Box 2)
      - no. 3, (photocopy), Summer 1962 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Fliers, Berkeley Poetry Conference; "San Francisco Poetry—The Rolling Renaissance" event (Box 2)
      Berkeley flier purchased, 2011.